<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Nazir's website</title>
    <description>This is a website i'm using to write my thoughts outside of twitter. Sometimes I put here my random side projects.</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 21:28:17 +0300</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 21:28:17 +0300</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Blockchain and a banking system</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post is in progress&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at banking systems in the majority of modern countries. Basically, it has 3 layers of data exchange:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(1) the Central Bank (CB) database, exchange between the CB and commercial banks, to keep comm banks level ledger;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(2) interbanking data exchange, exchange directly between banks, like SWIFT;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;(3) comm bank database, exchange between users of one bank, to keep users level ledger.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting that if we’re looking only at these data layers, w/o looking at other non-data mechanisms within this system, all layers are similar to layers we have at modern blockchain systems, for example, in Bitcoin/Lightning:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;L(1) - Bitcoin blockchain, exchange between main blockchain and lightning nodes;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;L(2) - Lightning payment channel, similar to SWIFT, exchange directly between lightning nodes;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;L(3) - Lightning nodes, similar to bank database, exchange between users of one node.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;History rhymes. Or not?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dashtiev&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;on my twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 17:28:14 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/general/2022/02/01/blockchain-and-a-banking-system.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/general/2022/02/01/blockchain-and-a-banking-system.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What is a gas fee</title>
        <description>&lt;h5 id=&quot;ethereum-basics&quot;&gt;Ethereum basics&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of gas fees, how they are calculated and how affect your transactions is fundamental to understanding how the Ethereum blockchain works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Basically, Ethereum is a decentralized computer that runs different types of transactions (txns) which could change the blockchain state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of txns are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Send ETH from one account to another&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interact with a smart contract, like swap a token on Uniswap&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All txns are initiated by accounts of the Ethereum network and basically are cryptographically signed instructions for the computer, the so-called Ethereum Virtual Machine (EVM).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;EVM is what defines the rules for computing a new valid state from block to block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’re two types of accounts in Ethereum:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Account managed by a human&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Account managed by a program (i.e. smart contract)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both types of accounts can:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Receive, hold and send ETH and tokens&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interact with deployed smart contracts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A smart contract is a program that “lives inside” a blockchain and can be triggered by txn from another account and execute many different actions, such as transferring tokens or even creating a new contract.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since each Ethereum txn requires computational resources to execute, each txn requires a fee and must be mined to become valid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;gas-basics&quot;&gt;Gas basics&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Gas” refers to the fee required to conduct a transaction on Ethereum successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simplest and most common txn type is a transfer of ETH from one account to another. Such txn requires 21000 gas to be executed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Complex txns, like smart contract creation or smart contract call can cost substantially higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a high level, the gas fee can be split into two different multipliers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gas fee] = [Gas units] * [Gas price per unit]&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gas units]&lt;/code&gt; is an amount of computational effort required to execute specific operations on the Ethereum network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gas price per unit]&lt;/code&gt; is a price depending on the network busyness and denoted in gwei.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gwei is 10^-9 ETH.&lt;br /&gt;
Gwei itself means giga-wei, and it’s equal to 10^9 wei.&lt;br /&gt;
Wei is the smallest unit of ETH, and it’s equal to 10^-18 ETH.&lt;br /&gt;
Wei itself is named after Wei Dai, creator of Bitcoin “predecessor” b-money, distributed electronic cash system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Calculating gas used to be very complicated, but it was simplified after EIP 1559 implementation (as part of the London Upgrade) in the middle of 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your wallet supports EIP 1559 (like Metamask), gas for your txn will be calculated as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gas price] = [Gas units] * ( [Base fee] + [Priority fee] )&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It this particular example:
&lt;code&gt;[Gas price] = 248688 * (168 + 2) * 10^-9 * ETH_price = $128&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/what-is-a-gas-fee/metamask-wallet.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Base fee]&lt;/code&gt; is set by the network. It increases and decreases automatically based on network busyness.
This fee gets burned when it’s paid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Priority fee]&lt;/code&gt; is optional and not burning. It goes to a miner as an incentive to process your txn sooner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, If you put 0 gwei for &lt;code&gt;[Priority fee]&lt;/code&gt; more likely there will be no reason for the miner to include your txn into the block.&lt;br /&gt;
Without this fee, miners would find it economically viable to mine empty blocks, as they would receive the same block reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can find actual block base fee and priority fees for different types of txn execution speed (e.g. low, average, high) on various websites.
For example here: &lt;a href=&quot;https://etherscan.io/gastracker&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://etherscan.io/gastracker&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/what-is-a-gas-fee/etherscan.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Max fee]&lt;/code&gt; includes both &lt;code&gt;[Base fee]&lt;/code&gt; and &lt;code&gt;[Priority fee]&lt;/code&gt; and it’s a maximum amount of fee you’d be willing to pay to a txn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Metamask initially sets this amount based on the previous block’s history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The higher &lt;code&gt;[Max fee]&lt;/code&gt; is, the more chances txn will be successful in case of a surge in blockchain use (i.e. [Base fee] increase) after txn is submitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;what-is-a-gas-limit-and-why-it-exists&quot;&gt;What is a gas limit and why it exists&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, now we know how fees per gas unit are produced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s move to the &lt;code&gt;[Gas limit]&lt;/code&gt; and how it differs from actual gas usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/what-is-a-gas-fee/gas-usage.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;[Gas limit]&lt;/code&gt; refers to the maximum amount of &lt;code&gt;[Gas units]&lt;/code&gt; you are willing to consume on a txn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your gas limit will be lower than the actual amount of gas units needed to execute a txn, txn will be unsuccessful. The EVM then reverts any changes, &lt;strong&gt;but the gas will be consumed&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we can exactly estimate a &lt;code&gt;[Gas limit]&lt;/code&gt; for a txn it will be equal to actual gas usage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, usually, due to various reasons, it’s very hard to estimate exactly how many gas units are needed to execute a particular txn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even two absolutely the same txns can have different gas usage because of different EVM states while executing.
Here’s an example:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ethereum.stackexchange.com/questions/44643/why-gas-used-are-different-for-same-transfer-tx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://ethereum.stackexchange.com/questions/44643/why-gas-used-are-different-for-same-transfer-tx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h5 id=&quot;final-words&quot;&gt;Final words&lt;/h5&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Txns are basically a list of instructions for EVM. And any instruction has a universally agreed cost in terms of gas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More details about these ‘costs’ and other implementations of the EVM can be found in an Ethereum Yellowpaper: &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ethereum.github.io/yellowpaper/paper.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://ethereum.github.io/yellowpaper/paper.pdf&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://localhost:4000/assets/images/what-is-a-gas-fee/yellowpaper.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want to go deeper on this topic you can start with Ethereum documentation:&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://ethereum.org/en/developers/docs/gas/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://ethereum.org/en/developers/docs/gas/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gas fees is definitely a great concept that showed credibility over many years, but the next big step in Ethereum adoption will be a new UI/UX layer where a regular user doesn’t even know about its existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dashtiev&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;on my twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 21:16:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/general/2022/01/11/what-is-a-gas-fee.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/general/2022/01/11/what-is-a-gas-fee.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Crowdworking and web3</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Crowdwork organizations are a very necessary part of our future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today companies like Mturk, Scale, Toloka, Hive and many others solving a crucial part of AI - data labeling. But crowd work is so much more than that and should drive other industries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core idea behind crowdwork tools is to divide a complex task into simple ones, give those simple tasks to many people, collect the results and use algorithms to combine them in one good result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples:&lt;br /&gt;
a) Labeling for CV (computer vision): take an image, send an image to many people, ask them to find needed objects and label them, collect results, use algorithms to keep the good results and ignore bad ones, combine in one result and give it back to the customer.&lt;br /&gt;
b) Labeling for CV v2: ask someone to label an image, send labeled image to many people, ask them to give binary answers is it correct or not, use algorithms to make a decision, if labeling was correct send a labeled image back to the customer. (b) is usually cheaper than (a).&lt;br /&gt;
c) Catalog mapping for e-commerce goods: take goods w/ descriptions, send to people, ask to attach the category, then ask many other people to answer is it correct category for a particular good or not, use algorithms to make a decision for each good-category, send results back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of the examples above is just a part of bigger pipelines that companies can build using crowdwork tools.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ML models usually are part of the software stack and can solve some tasks in combinations with humans (HITL) or w/o them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today crowdwork tools are mainly used in AI/ML industry to prepare datasets for machine learning, but I believe crowd work applications could be used in a lot of other industries: support, call-centers, maps creation, paperwork automation, back-office functions, accounting, etc. It’s all just a tiny piece of the addressable market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The huge BPO industry, &lt;strong&gt;~$250B&lt;/strong&gt; in 2021, could be almost completely replaced by such crowdwork organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of micro-tasks workers are living in Third World countries and such jobs are one of the few opportunities for them to be a part of the global economy.
And a big part of profits taken in such markets like BPO can be distributed directly to all those workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides that crowdwork tools could be also a way to gain knowledge from well-paid and experienced individuals, e.g. doctors, to build systems based on their combined knowledge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Read this small article about it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2016/06/15/alphabets-eric-schmidt-predicts-what-spark-the-next-100-billion-firm.html&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now with web3 taking off, I’m thinking about how crowdworking/crowdsourcing idea can evolve further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It seems like both these decentralization-driven narratives should help each other to thrive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine a crowdwork-based DAO where all the software for “dispatching” micro-tasks and algorithms to verify the results are made by the community and open-sourced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People who will work in such DAO to solve tasks will be paid in crypto-native currency and have governance rights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This crypto token should be backed by real profits from the already existing market and thus have real value behind it from the first days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Developers who will work on the product side of this tool will be also incentivized by this token, which aligns them with workers who perform tasks on the platform and puts both sides in a very short loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think right now we’re in the moment when both crowdworking and web3 movements should be combined to try to build something really meaningful for a lot of people around the globe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re working on something like that or want to explore this idea further, let’s connect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dashtiev&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;on my twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 20:06:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/general/2022/01/04/crowdworking-and-web3.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/general/2022/01/04/crowdworking-and-web3.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Why crypto matters</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Imagine the world where people don’t lie and cheat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world where people need less negotiation, less lawyers, less compliance procedures, less audits, less bureaucracy. The world where all these freed-up resources can be used to improve productivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is exactly what crypto brings to the world - &lt;strong&gt;a system where people can be excluded out of the decision making processes and replaced by trustless open sourced apps, which don’t lie and cheat&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dashtiev&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;on my twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2021 15:42:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/general/2021/10/21/why-crypto-matters.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/general/2021/10/21/why-crypto-matters.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Apps come first, then comes infrastructure</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;A breakthrough app which is built for the first time on top of old infrastructure driving the market to create new infrastructure to make it possible to run better and scale faster this new kind of the app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After, this new level infrastructure gives the ability to create new early-stage breakthrough apps, which again drives infrastructure to grow to the next level.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s happening again and again within the different industries. And it’s better to know at which stage your industry is right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe, a couple of industries I’m interested in, like logistics, robotics and space are right now at the end of the latest infrastructure-grow cycle and within the next 10 years we mainly should see new breakthrough applications to appear within them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally posted &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/dashtiev&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;on my twitter&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 13:11:00 +0300</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/general/2021/07/18/apps-come-first.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/general/2021/07/18/apps-come-first.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>general</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
